We're talking about the fact that carcinogenic agents
damage DNA, and when they damage DNA,
there are some key regulatory systems that can be damaged.
One key regulatory system that can be damaged
are proto-oncogenes, and when they're mutated,
they become oncogenes, and they can then result
in the formation of a tumor.
Another key regulatory system that can be damaged
are tumor suppressor genes.
And what do tumor suppressor genes do?
They regulate cell growth.
And so this is the discussion that we now want to have,
and that is what are tumor suppressor genes
and how could they result in tumor formation.
So the key idea here is that tumor suppressor genes,
they decrease, i.e. suppress, the risk of tumor formation.
And the two classic examples are p53 and retinoblastoma.
So let's take a moment to discuss each of these.
Now what does p53 do?
It regulates the cell cycle.
In particular, it regulates the G1 to S phase.
And the way I think about p53 is sort of like a traffic cop.
Let's imagine, let's take a whiteboard,
let's imagine that the cell would like to go
from the G1 to the S phase.
So before it can go from G1 to S phase,
it's got to sort of go past p53.
All right, now, when it walks past p53,
p53 is like a traffic cop,
and it basically says, all right, show me your DNA.
And when the cell shows p53 its DNA,
there's two possibilities.
If p53 looks at the DNA of the cell
and sees that the DNA is mutated,
then p53 will actually blow a molecular whistle,
and it'll call in DNA repair enzymes
and repair the DNA mutations
so that before the cell goes into S phase,
the DNA is repaired.
That's one possibility.
Another possibility is that p53 looks at the DNA of the cell
and says, there is no way this cell is going to go into S phase
because this cell's got way too many mutations
and we can't repair these mutations.
So in that case, what would p53 do?
It'll blow another molecular whistle,
and it'll call in a molecule called Bax.
And guess what Bax does?
Bax goes in, and it destroys BCL2.
So Bax goes in, and it destroys BCL2.
And you know what BCL2 is?
BCL2 is the molecule that stabilizes the mitochondrial membrane
so that cytochrome C doesn't leak out.
So if you knock out BCL2,
cytochrome C will actually leak out of the mitochondria,
and when cytochrome C leaks out of the mitochondria,
it will activate the caspases,
which will then create apoptosis of the cell.
And so p53 has the ability to induce apoptosis
when there's severe DNA mutation in a cell.
And again, the idea is you want that cell to undergo apoptosis
because it's got so many DNA mutations
that there's a risk that it could produce at cancer.
All right, so let's read together.
What do I say here?
P53 regulates the cell cycle,
in particular progression from the G1 to S phase.
Now again, what does p53 do?
In response to DNA damage,
p53 upregulates DNA repair enzymes.
All right?
However, if repair is not possible,
p53 induces apoptosis.
And I've already explained how apoptosis would occur.
Now, it's important to note that both copies of p53
must be knocked out for tumor formation.
And the way I think about this
is it's sort of like an intersection, right?
These are traffic cops,
and if one traffic cop goes to lunch,
then the other traffic cop can sort of man the intersection,
and there wouldn't really be any accidents.
But if both traffic cops are not at the intersection,
the intersection becomes chaotic,
and there's an increased risk for accidents.
And so the only way to develop tumors
is to knock out both copies of p53.
And that's called Knudsen's two-hit hypothesis.
All right?
That both copies of p53 must be knocked out
for tumor formation is this notion
that both copies must be knocked out
is called Knudsen's two-hit hypothesis.
Now, loss of p53 is seen in more than 50% of cancers.
Usually, both copies of p53 are knocked out somatically.
However, it is possible that a patient could inherit
one bad copy of p53 from a parent,
and that's called the Lee-Fraumeni syndrome.
And the Lee-Fraumeni syndrome is associated
with an increased risk for multiple types
of carcinomas and sarcomas.
So that's a little bit about p53.
Another important tumor suppressor gene
is retinoblastoma.
And retinoblastoma also regulates progression
from G1 to S phase.
And the idea here is that,
I'll just do this as a picture,
when the cell wants to go from G1 to S phase,
one of the key molecules that it needs
in order to do that is called E2F.
So E2F is necessary to go from G1 to S phase,
and gets who holds on to E2F.
So E2F is normally bound by retinoblastoma.
And in order for E2F to be released,
retinoblastoma must be phosphorylated.
And when retinoblastoma is phosphorylated,
it becomes very happy,
and it releases E2F,
and the release of E2F then allows the cell
to go from G1 to S phase.
So that is the sort of the normal function
of retinoblastoma.
Now if there's a mutation in retinoblastoma,
then E2F is free,
and the free E2F will allow cells
to easily go from the G1 to the S phase,
and that will then result in the formation of a tumor.
So this is why loss of retinoblastoma
increases or results in the formation of tumor.
So let's go back and read.
So retinoblastoma regulates progression
from G1 to the S phase.
Retinoblastoma holds the E2F transcription factor,
which is necessary for a transition to the S phase.
Normally, E2F is released
when retinoblastoma is phosphorylated.
And who phosphorylates retinoblastoma?
Retinoblastoma, cyclin D, CDK4 complex,
which has the ability to phosphorylate proteins.
If retinoblastoma is mutated,
that results in constitutively free E2F.
So for E2F will be free,
and that allows for uncontrolled progression
through the cell cycle.
So that's the consequence of retinoblastoma mutation.
Now again, same idea.
Both copies of retinoblastoma must be knocked out
for tumor formation,
and that's called Knudsen's two-hit hypothesis.
If a patient has sporadic mutations
resulting in both copies of retinoblastoma being knocked out,
the patient will develop unilateral retinoblastoma.
However, if the patient has germline mutation of retinoblastoma,
the patient is more likely to develop bilateral retinoblastoma,
and they also can develop osteosarcoma.
Now, I think this requires a little bit of explanation,
so I'm going to take a moment to back away
and explain a principle here.
Now let's take,
so what is retinoblastoma?
Retinoblastoma is a tumor
that develops in the back of the eye,
and I've included a picture here in your text,
and here is the eyeball,
and this is here,
the tumor sort of in the back of the eye
arising from the retina,
and that's a retinoblastoma.
Now let's take for a moment
a very simple example.
I'm going to go to my whiteboard here
and just explain something.
Let's pretend that there is a patient,
and we're going to draw a couple copies of retinoblastoma.
So this is retinoblastoma.
These are normal retinoblastoma genes
on their chromosomes,
and retinoblastoma,
one copy is inherited from mom,
and one copy is inherited from dad,
and so this is a child,
and they've got two normal copies of retinoblastoma.
Okay?
Now they've got,
let's say in the back of the eye,
they've got billions of cells
sitting in the back of the eye,
and each cell has two normal copies
of retinoblastoma.
Now in order for a tumor to develop,
one copy of retinoblastoma
must be knocked out, right?
And then in the exact same cell,
that one cell in a billion,
the second copy must also be knocked out.
That's the only way,
by knocking out both copies,
that the tumor retinoblastoma
is going to form.
All right?
So what's the probability
that one in a billion cells
would actually get hit,
the exact same cell would get hit twice,
and both copies would be knocked out?
It's essentially zero.
And that's why retinoblastoma
is essentially almost never seen.
It's a very, very rare tumor,
and it's very unlikely
that you would ever see it
except on examinations.
And so that's why I say here in your text
that a sporadic mutation,
the most,
the most those patients would ever develop
is a unilateral retinoblastoma.
Now let's take the other extreme,
and that is let's say that
the patient has,
I don't know,
retinoblastoma,
okay,
here and here.
These are the father and the mother.
And let's pretend
that one of the parents
has a bad gene.
We'll put an X through it.
Now what's going to happen
is that the child
is going to inherit
one bad gene
and one good gene,
correct?
Let's just make that as an example
that they happen to inherit
one bad gene
and one good gene.
Now in the back of the eye,
every single cell,
all the one billion cells,
just as an example,
in the back of the eye
are actually going to contain
or already begin with
one bad gene
because they inherited
one bad gene.
Now what's the probability
that an additional mutation
could come in
and hit the good gene?
Sorry,
this is a good gene here.
What's the probability
that that could happen?
It's pretty likely.
It's not,
it wouldn't be unheard of.
And so these patients,
because the whole
back of the eye
is sort of like a field
ready to be mutated,
if any one of these cells
gets hit,
they're going to get
a retinoblastoma.
And similarly,
if any one of these
billions of cells
in the back of the other eye
get hit,
they're going to get
another retinoblastoma.
And that's not too hard
to occur
because there's so many cells
that could easily
get mutated.
And so that's why
patients with a germline mutation,
with a germline mutation,
have an increased risk
of usually get
bilateral retinoblastoma.
And what's also important
for examinations,
there's an increased risk
of osteosarcoma.
So that's something
to be familiar with as well.
Okay.
And the last,
or the third,
regulatory system
are regulators
of apoptosis.
Now,
remember that apoptosis
needs to be regulated.
And why does it need
to be regulated?
Because apoptosis,
you want apoptosis
to not occur
in a normal cell.
You don't want
a normal cell to die.
So you want to prevent
apoptosis in a normal cell.
But you want to promote
apoptosis in mutated cells
because you don't want
cells whose DNA
cannot be repaired.
If there's DNA
and it cannot be repaired,
you want apoptosis
to occur
in that mutated cell.
And so apoptosis
is highly regulated.
One of the important
regulators of apoptosis
is BCL2.
Now,
what does BCL2 do?
I've told you this
time and time again,
but we'll repeat it
one more time.
BCL2 stabilizes
the mitochondrial membrane
so that cytochrome C
cannot be released.
If BCL2 gets disrupted,
cytochrome C
can leak out,
which then activates
caspases
and subsequently results
in apoptosis.
So this is BCL2.
Now,
one of the high-yield
principles to be familiar
with regarding BCL2
is that BCL2
is overexpressed
in follicular lymphoma.
Okay,
let's go back.
Now,
basically,
the idea here
is that in follicular lymphoma
you get something
called a 14-18 translocation.
Guess what sits on
chromosome 14?
Yep,
immunoglobulin heavy chain.
Okay,
and guess what sits
on chromosome 18?
BCL2.
You have to know
that BCL2
sits on chromosome 18.
Well,
you would know that
because of the 14-18 translocation
you know that BCL2
is involved in follicular lymphoma.
So these are some things
to be aware of.
Now,
this translocation,
when BCL2
goes to the immunoglobulin
heavy chain region
because we're dealing
with B cells,
this is occurring
in B cells,
then what's going to happen
is BCL2
will be overexpressed.
And then,
because BCL2
is overexpressed,
apoptosis will not occur
because the
mitochondrial membrane
will be
super stabilized
because you've got
super amounts
of BCL2.
Now,
that's not really
a problem
because the vast majority
of cells,
and for the most part
B cells,
you don't want them
to apoptose anyway.
However,
there is one region
in the body
where you actually want
a lot of apoptosis
and that is
in the follicle.
Now,
why do you want that?
Because remember,
what's happening
in the follicle?
In the follicle,
the B cells
are undergoing
somatic hypermutation.
What's somatic hypermutation?
That's a random
generation of mutations
within the B cell
so that you can
increase the
antibody,
the diversity
of the antibodies
being produced
by the B cell.
So,
somatic hypermutation
is a
desired state,
is a desired occurrence
within the lymph node,
but if the mutations
fail,
you want those cells
to die.
That's the mechanism
by which cells die.
So,
we could state it otherwise.
When B cells,
B cells are born
in the bone marrow
and they're born
as naive B cells
and then they go
to college.
And where do they
go to college?
They go to college
in the lymph node.
And,
in the lymph node,
when they go
to college,
the way by which
they fail in college
is somatic,
the test in college
is somatic hypermutation.
Are you able
to produce
a newly mutated
immunoglobulin
that might be able
to react against
antigen?
And if you're not
able to do that,
then you have to fail.
And the way by which
the lymph node fails
the B cell
and removes it
is apoptosis.
So,
if the B cell
is not able
to undergo apoptosis
in the follicle,
it's going to just
pile up.
And as the B cells
pile up,
that's going to produce
a follicular lymphoma.
Okay?
And so,
one of the key features
of follicular lymphoma
is that the cells
are not apoptosing.
And the reason
they're not apoptosing
is because
there is a
markedly increased
BCL2.
And so,
the cells can't
apoptose
because the mitochondrial
membrane is super
stabilized.
So,
that's BCL2
and its relationship
to follicular lymphoma.
A few other
important features
concerning tuber
development.
We've sort of
concluded our
discussion of the
key regulatory
systems,
but there are a
few other features
to be familiar with.
First of all,
telomerase
is a necessary
enzyme
for cell
immortality.
Now,
let's go back
and remind ourselves.
First of all,
cells,
when they divide
normally,
each time a cell
divides,
its telomere
is shortened.
And telomeres
are at the
very end of
the DNA
of each
chromosome,
and the telomeres
shorten,
and every time
they shorten,
eventually that
results in
senescence.
So,
the continuous
shortening of
the telomeres
with serial cell
divisions results
in senescence
in which a cell
basically shuts
down and stops
dividing.
Cancer cells
can't stop
dividing.
They need to
keep dividing,
and the cells are
basically immortal.
That's how
cancer works.
And so,
cancer often
has upregulated
telomerase,
which preserves
the telomeres
so that
cancer cells
can avoid
senescence.
And that's
an important
general principle
concerning
cancer cells,
that often
telomerase is
upregulated.
Another important
feature of cancer
is that it
requires angiogenesis.
Tumor,
if it's going to
grow,
is going to
require blood.
And so,
fibroblast growth
factor,
which is again
an important
angiogenic factor,
despite the name
fibroblast growth
factor,
and vascular
endothelial growth
factor are
commonly produced
by tumor cells
to ensure
tumor growth
and survival.
And then the
final principle
that I'd like
to highlight
is that tumor
cells are
mutated,
correct?
And so,
if they're
mutated,
they're going
to be producing
abnormal proteins.
And if they're
producing abnormal
proteins,
those abnormal
proteins are going
to be expressed
on MHC class 1.
And one way
by which the
human body
can deal
with tumors
is when
there's abnormal
protein present
on MHC class 1,
the CD8-positive
T cells come in
and they can
kill the tumor.
And so,
CD8-positive T cells
and MHC 1
are highly important
for something
called immune
surveillance of
tumor cells,
okay?
So,
one of the ways
by which tumors
can avoid
this immune
surveillance
is by down-regulating
MHC 1.
If MHC 1
is down-regulated,
the abnormal
proteins being
produced by the
tumor won't be
expressed on the
surface and the
CD8-positive T cells
won't be able to
come in and kill
those tumor cells.
So,
that's one way
by which tumor
cells can avoid
immune surveillance.
Another important
association here
or derivative
principle here is
that when patients
have immunodeficiency,
that's going to
increase the risk
for cancer because
immune surveillance
won't be
functioning properly
and immune
surveillance is
an important
mechanism for
removal of tumor
cells or
for protecting
a host
from the
development
of tumor.
But I would say
very important
to remember here
that CD8-positive
T cells play
an important role
in immune
surveillance by
recognizing
aberrant protein
present on MHC
class 1.
And that really
concludes,
that's going to
conclude this
particular section,
relatively long
section but
contains a lot
of high yield
and so we spent
a little bit of
time here but
hopefully it'll
pay off as we
move through the
course.
So we'll go
ahead and stop
here and the
next section will
be a discussion
on how tumors
can progress once
they develop the
necessary mutations
to actually form a
tumor.
So we'll
see you next
time.
We'll be right back.